Today's daf is קכג Kuf Chaf Gimmel 123, and we pick up
with,
you know let's start from the second to the last line of
קכג Kuf Chaf Gimmel עמוד ב Amud Bet back. We might as
well just take it from there. Okay, so we're now shifting to
a discussion of somewhat of a halachic, we seem to be sort
of moving in and out between halachic and aggadic discussions, and we
start with a halachic question but it's going to lead to a
certain nice big segment of אגדתא. Aggadeta. So picking up from two
lines from the bottom of קכג Kuf Chaf Gimmel עמוד ב, Amud
Bet,
we say the following. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, לתת לו פי שנים,
Latet lo pi shnayim, so the בכור bechor gets a double portion.
פי שנים כאחד, Pi shnayim ke'echad, a double of any individual son.
So if there are five sons, the classical way it is is
you divide it amongst, you create six portions, so each son gets
one and this one gets two. אתה אומר פי שנים כאחד, Atah
omer pi shnayim ke'echad, you say double any other son, או אינו
אלא פי שנים בכל הנכסים, o eino ela pi shnayim bechol hanechasim,
maybe it's double whatever everybody else gets combined. Okay, wow, that would
be a lot. So if there were five sons, you would basically
make 15 portions. Each of the sons would get one and this
guy would get ten, right, because he would get double what everybody
else, not of each individual one, the double of them all combined.
Okay, you got the difference? So it's a huge difference. All right,
there you go. Okay, so it's a huge difference. והדין הוא, Vehadin
hu, now
it makes sense. חלקו עם אחד וחלקו עם חמשה, Chelko im echad
vechelko im chamishah, let's compare a case of what do you have
in the most simplest case, one other son, and then extrapolate to
the case of there are you know a total of six kids,
of five other kids. מה חלקו עם אחד פי שנים כאחד, Mah
chelko im echad pi shnayim ke'echad, when there's one other son, he
gets double. If it's ראובן Reuven and שמעון, Shimon, ראובן Reuven gets
double what שמעון Shimon has, what the individual son has. אף חלקו
עם חמשה פי שנים כאחד, Af chelko im chamishah pi shnayim ke'echad,
so if there are five other brothers,
he gets double what every individual brother gets. Of course you could
say the exact opposite. או כלך לדרך זו, O kalach lederech zo,
or maybe take the argument argument.
חלקו עם אחד וחלקו עם חמשה, Chelko im echad vechelko im chamishah,
let's compare when he has one brother when he has five brothers.
מה חלקו עם אחד פי שנים בכל הנכסים, Mah chelko im echad
pi shnayim bechol hanechasim, when it's ראובן Reuven and שמעון, Shimon, ראובן
Reuven gets double what one brother has, but he also gets double
what all the brothers have, because one is the same as all,
right? So let's interpret it, ראובן Reuven gets two, שמעון Shimon gets
one, that means he gets double what everyone combined gets rather than
he gets double what one person gets. Let's read it that way.
Okay, אף
חלקו עם חמשה פי שנים בכל הנכסים, Af chelko im chamishah pi
shnayim bechol hanechasim, so if there are five brothers, each one would
get one portion and he would get ten portions. Okay, so תלמוד
לומר, Talmud lomar, והיה ביום הנחילו את בניו, Vehayah beyom hanchilo et
banav, it will be on the day that he bequeaths to his
children,
את אשר יהיה לו, et asher yihyeh lo, right, so it says
and so the extra word when he bequeaths, it's enough to say
when he bequeaths, so and בניו banav is all of his children.
הטיל הכתוב נחלה אצל אחים, Hitil hakatuv nachalah etzel achim, to tell
you there's a that to tell you to like that the other
brothers have a significant stake in the נחלה. nachalah. So
אי אתה יכול לדונו כלשון האחרון אלא כלשון הראשון, ee atah yachol
leduno kelashon ha'acharon ela kelashon harishon, you should not go by the
second interpretation which gives the other brothers a trivial portion in the
inheritance compared to him, he has double all of them combined, no,
ביום הנחילו את בניו, Beyom hanchilo et banav, sort of puts front
and center all of the brothers get a significant stake, so he
gets double any individual brother but not double all of the brothers
combined. ואומר, Veomer, and here's the other evidence to that. ובני ראובן
בכור ישראל, Uvnei Reuven bechor Yisrael, this is from דברי הימים, Divrei
Hayamim, the sons of ראובן Reuven the firstborn of ישראל, Yisrael, of
Jacob, כי הוא הבכור, ki hu habechor,
he was the firstborn. ובחללו יצועי אביו, Uvechalelo yetzuei aviv, and when
he desecrated his father's bed, נתנה בכורתו לבני יוסף, nitnah bechorato livnei
Yosef, the right of firstborn meaning he still is the firstborn but
the privileges of the firstborn or or the benefits were given to
the children of יוסף, Yosef, בן ישראל, ben Yisrael, יוסף Yosef the
son of ישראל. Yisrael. ולא להתייחס לבכורה, Velo lehityaches labechorah, this is
still quoting from the פסוק, pasuk, not that he not to be
identified as the firstborn. The firstborn is ראובן, Reuven, that's why it
starts with ובני ראובן בכור ישראל. Uvnei Reuven bechor Yisrael. So who
is the firstborn, we're not going to say יוסף Yosef is the
firstborn. In terms of like a personal identity, ראובן Reuven is the
firstborn, but the benefits of the firstborn get given to יוסף. Yosef.
Okay, so now we know from there that יוסף Yosef gets the
benefits of the firstborn. ואומר, Veomer, and another פסוק pasuk says, כי
יהודה גבר באחיו ולנגיד ממנו, ki Yehudah gavar be'echav ulenagid mimenu,
and because יהודה Yehudah was the sort of you know mighty of
his brothers and to be a ruler over them, והבכורה ליוסף, vehabechorah
leYosef,
and יוסף Yosef gets the right, the privileges of the firstborn. נאמר
בכורה ליוסף ונאמר בכורה לדורות, Ne'emar bechorah leYosef vene'emar bechorah ledorot, so
it was said for יוסף Yosef and it was said for the
דורות, dorot, right, that it says that you know that the בכור
bechor gets פי שנים. pi shnayim. So מה בכורה... Mah bechorah... מה
בכורה bechorah, האמורה ליוסף פי שנים כאחד *Mah bechorah ha'amurah le'Yosef pi
shenayim ke'echad*? Now what יוסף Yosef *Yosef* we know got a double
portion from any individual brother. How do we know where did יוסף
Yosef *Yosef* get a double portion from an individual brother?
Where do we see that יוסף Yosef *Yosef* got a double portion?
אפרים ומנשה *Ephraim u'Menashe*, he got two tribes. Okay, so he did
not get it, it wasn't like there were eleven tribes and יוסף
Yosef. *Yosef* got twenty-two tribes. Okay, יוסף Yosef *Yosef* or whatever, יוסף
Yosef
*Yosef* got double of one individual brother.
Okay, so מה בכורה האמורה ליוסף פי שנים כאחד אף בכורה האמורה
לדורות פי שנים כאחד *Mah bechorah ha'amurah le'Yosef pi shenayim ke'echad af
bechorah ha'amurah ledorot pi shenayim ke'echad*. ואומר *Ve'omer*, and a פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* says, and here we're going to see where it means double
of an individual brother. Now is it two tribes or is it
double the portion in the land of ישראל *Israel*? Okay, so anyway,
so another פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says speaking about the land, ואני נתתי
לך שכם אחד על אחיך *Va'ani natati lecha Shechem echad al achecha*.
I, no, I think the...
שכם אחד *Shechem echad*?
Yeah, I think that's the, I mean I've read the פסוק Pasuk
*pasuk*. שכם *Shechem* I think, anyway, it's... שכם אחד *Shechem echad*. Anyway,
ואני נתתי לך שכם אחד על אחיך *Va'ani natati lecha Shechem echad
al achecha*, I have given you one שכם *Shechem*, which means, I
know some say it refers to actually the city of שכם *Shechem*,
which they, you know, conquered, or one portion over your brothers, אשר
לקחתי מיד האמורי בחרבי ובקשתי *asher lakachti miyad ha'Emori becharbi u'vekashti*, which
I've taken from the האמורי *Emori* with my sword and with my
bow. Right, you know, so here Shimon and Levi are the ones
that conquer it, and and now יעקב Yaakov *Yaakov* is sort of
saying I took it with my sword and bow. I mean, Shimon
and Levi took it with a, you know, ruse, and now he's
saying and I'm giving it, if it's referring to actual שכם *Shechem*,
or it might be referring to a portion, but anyway I'm giving
it to you, יוסף Yosef *Yosef*. But he's giving יוסף Yosef *Yosef*
one portion. He's not giving יוסף Yosef? *Yosef* equal to what everybody
else got, right? One portion presumably means one unit and compared to
any other unit that any other tribe got, so it's double an
individual tribe. One minute, ובחרבו ובקשתו לקחתי *u'vecharbo u'vekashto lakachti*? Did he
really take it with his sword and with his arrow? I mean
and with his bow? Did יעקב Yaakov *Yaakov* fight some war? No,
אבל כבר נאמר *aval kvar ne'emar*, כי לא בקשתי אבטח וחרבי לא
תושיעני *Ki lo vekashti evtach vecharbi lo toshieni*. Not with my, you
know, bow will I have to, will I put my trust and
my sword will not save me, you know, and clearly יעקב Yaakov
*Yaakov* of course was not the one going in and being violent
and waging wars, his trust was in God. אלא חרבי זו תפילה
tefillah *Ella charbi zo tefillah*. No, my חרב *cherev* is my, is
my, is my prayer. קשתי זו בקשה *Kashti zo bakashah*. And קשתי
*kashti* is my, my, you know,
my bequest, or not bequest, my request to God, my, you know,
impeaching of God, my, my beseeching of God. So not exactly clear
like it's a nice play of course on the word קשתי *kashti*
and בקשתי *bakashati*, right? Not exactly clear what they're referring to. So
if you look at the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam*, three lines down in
the narrow lines, he says זו תפילה שהתפלל יעקב Yaakov על בניו
ושזכה לקנות הבכורה מעשיו בתפילתו *zo tefillah shehitpalel Yaakov al banav veshizacha
liknot habechorah me'Esav bitfillato*. So, you know, sort of obviously this is
not in the פסוקים pesukim. *pesukim*, but it's sort of saying, well,
in general he prayed, you know, on behalf of his children and
he prayed to get עשיו *Esav*'s בכורה *bechorah*, so by taking עשיו
*Esav*'s בכורה *bechorah* now he's giving that right to יעקב Yaakov *Yaakov*,
so we're reading a whole narrative in there that, and I mean
to, to יוסף Yosef. *Yosef*, that what he's giving יוסף Yosef *Yosef*
is what he prayed, is what the fact that he managed to
get the בכורה *bechorah* from עשיו *Esav*. Anyway, but he's saying still
that he gave יוסף Yosef. *Yosef* an extra portion. Okay, and let's
just finish this. Okay, מאי ואומר *Mai ve'omer*? What does it mean?
Why do you have to quote all these פסוקים *pesukim*? You know,
once you linked it to יוסף Yosef. *Yosef*, you see that it
means double an individual brother, not double all the brothers combined. וכי
תימא *Vechi teima*, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to tell you
here because any individual פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* wouldn't have necessarily proven it.
וכי תימא היי לדרבי יוחנן בן ברוקה דאתא *Vechi teima hai led'Rabbi
Yochanan ben Beroka de'ata*, ביום הנחילו את בניו *beyom hanchilo et banav*
might not have come to say that the other brothers get a
substantial amount, that he gets double an individual but not double all
of them. Maybe ביום הנחילו את בניו *beyom hanchilo et banav* is
coming to tell you like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, בן ברוקה *Rabbi
Yochanan ben Beroka* that he can like change the proportions among his
sons, remember that was mentioned yesterday, that according to רבי יוחנן בן
ברוקה *Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka* the תורה Torah *Torah* gives him a
right to actively bequeath
and he can actually change the proportions among his sons, who gets
how much. So maybe that's what it's saying and not to say
that the sons get a significant amount.
Where were we? So תלמוד לומר *Talmud lomar*, one minute, וכי תימא
היי לדרבי יוחנן בן ברוקה דאתא תא שמע ובני ראובן Reuven, בכור
bechor ישראל *Vechi teima hai led'Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka de'ata ta shema
u'venei Reuven bechor Yisrael*. So that's why we're going to bring evidence
from the idea that יוסף Yosef *Yosef* gets double and it means
double an individual son. וכי תימא בכורה מבכורתו לא גמרינן *Vechi teima
bechorah mibechorato lo gamrinan*. No, there it says בכורתו *bechorato*, his firstborn,
so you can't link it to the word בכורה *bechorah* כי לא
משפט הבכורה *ki lo mishpat habechorah* in the תורה Torah *Torah*, maybe
those are not similar enough to link. תא שמע והבכורה ליוסף *Ta
shema vehabechorah le'Yosef*. Here's the word בכורה *bechorah* that applies to יוסף
Yosef *Yosef*, and we have the word לא משפט הבכורה *lo mishpat
habechorah* in the תורה Torah *Torah*, so the same way יוסף Yosef
*Yosef* is double an individual brother, here too it's double an individual
brother. וכי תימא יוסף Yosef גופיה ממאי דפי שנים כאחד הוא *Vechi
teima Yosef gufeih mimai despi shenayim ke'echad hu*? How do you know
יוסף Yosef *Yosef* got double an individual brother? Maybe יוסף Yosef. *Yosef*
got double all the brothers? תא שמע ואני נתתי לך שכם אחד
על אחיך *Ta shema va'ani natati lecha Shechem echad al achecha*. I
only gave you one portion more than your brothers, right? So I
didn't give you equal to what all of them got. I got
you one portion more than they got. אמר ליה Amar lei: *Amar
lei* רב פפא *Rav Pappa* לאביי *l'Abaye* אימא *eima* דיקלא בעלמא *dikla
b'alma*. So maybe we should read it in the opposite direction. If
he says שכם אחד *shechem echad*, what is שכם *shechem*? It's some
type of a portion. Maybe it's like I gave you a palm
tree, I gave you a little extra thing. How do you know
that it means you got really an equal amount, fully equal to
any individual brother? אמר ליה Amar lei: *Amar lei* הלה קרא *hala
kra*, which is where we all would have gone right away, which
is where Eli went right away. אפרים ומנשה כראובן ושמעון יהיו לי
*Ephraim u'Menashe k'Reuven v'Shimon yihiyu li*. Just look at the fact that
יוסף Yosef *Yosef* got two tribes. So the fact that he says
you got your two sons equal two tribes means that יוסף Yosef
*Yosef*'s idea of getting the right of the בכורה *bechora* was that
he got double what any individual son got. Okay, so the פי
שנים *pi shnayim* is not double all of the children combined; it's
not they got 11 tribes and he got 22 tribes. It is
double an individual son. And that is the and that we learn
from יוסף Yosef *Yosef* and that is the הלכה Halacha. *halacha* of
בכור bechor *bechor*. Rabbi D, you wanted to say something?
No, no, no.
Okay, yes, Davey, a question.
The question of יוסף Yosef? *Yosef* being the firstborn, how does that
work? The actual...
No, that's why the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* said. We don't refer to
him as the firstborn. וראובן הוא בכור bechor ישראל *v'Reuven hu bechor
Yisrael* but he gets the privileges, similar to יעקב Yaakov, *Ya'akov* and
עשו Eisav *Eisav*. I mean we're not actually saying that some person
is not the firstborn but we're giving him all the privileges of
the firstborn and that gets passed over to יוסף Yosef. *Yosef*. Yeah.
But you could still say that's only in the case where he's
also בכור bechor מאם *bechor me'eim*. I guess.
You could have. Okay. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says like this. Okay. So now, so that was resolving that הלכה
*halacha* question of what's the definition of פי שנים *pi shnayim*? But
now that we've introduced this sort of אגדתא Agaddeta *Agadata* talking about
the children of יעקב Yaakov. *Ya'akov*, we're going to have a nice
little digression, piece of אגדתא *Agadata* coming up. Okay, so בעי מיניה
*bei minei* רב חלבו *Rav Helbo* מרבי שמואל Shmuel. בר נחמני *me'Rabbi
Shmuel bar Nachmani*. רב חלבו *Rav Helbo* asked from שמואל בר נחמני
*Shmuel bar Nachmani*. I lost my place. מה ראה יעקב Yaakov. שנטל
בכורה מראובן ונתנה ליוסף *ma ra'ah Ya'akov she'natal bechora mi'Reuven u'netana l'Yosef*?
What motivated him to take it away from ראובן Reuven *Reuven* and
give it to יוסף Yosef. *Yosef*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
מה ראה *ma ra'ah*. What do you mean what motivated him? It's
right there in the פסוקים *psukim* in דברי הימים Divrei Hayamim? *Divrei
HaYamim*. ובחללו יצועי אביו כתיב Ksiv, *u'v'chalelo yitzuei aviv ktiv*. Because because
he desecrated his father's bed, he took it away from ראובן Reuven
*Reuven*. אלא מה ראה שניתנה ליוסף *ella ma ra'ah she'nitna l'Yosef*? I
get why he took it away from ראובן Reuven *Reuven*, why did
he give it to יוסף Yosef. *Yosef*? So he says אמשול לך
משל *emshol l'cha mashal*. Let me give you a parable. למה הדבר
דומה *l'ma hadavar domeh*? What can this be compared to? לבעל הבית
שגידל יתום בתוך ביתו *l'ba'al
habayit she'gidal yatom b'toch beito*. A homeowner raised an orphan in his
home. לימים העשיר אותו יתום *l'yamim he'eshir oto yatom*. Then the orphan
went off and he made his way in the world, he became
a millionaire. ואמר אהנה לבעל הבית מנכסי *v'amar ahena l'ba'al habayit mi'nechasai*.
You know what? Let me now return the favor, let me now
give some of my wealth and benefit the person, the nice man
who raised me. So who is the בעל הבית *ba'al habayit* and
who is the יתום *yatom* here? It's very interesting. יוסף *Yosef* is
the בעל הבית *ba'al habayit*. יעקב Yaakov. *Ya'akov* excellent, you figured that
out יעקב Yaakov *Ya'akov* is the orphan, because יעקב Yaakov. *Ya'akov* comes
down to מצרים Mitzrayim, *Mitzrayim*, he has no wealth, no
property, he's dispossessed from his home, he's taken in by יוסף *Yosef*.
יוסף *Yosef* is the provider.
So then at the end of his life, יעקב Yaakov, *Ya'akov* now
has something to give back. He has the בכורה *bechora* to give,
and he's going to give it to יוסף *Yosef*. Okay, so that's
why. So which is interesting, because it is so like fateful in
terms of the whole destiny like if you would or structure of
the future Jewish nation and it's making it very personal. I mean
the taking away from ראובן Reuven *Reuven* was also very personal.
So that's quite
interesting about how those... I mean that's always the sort of thing,
מעשה אבות סימן לבנים *ma'aseh avot siman labanim*, the personal dynamics of
the forefathers affect the whole future like structure and identity of the
nation. Okay, so אמר ליה Amar lei: ואי לאו דחטא ראובן לא
מהני ליה ליוסף
ולא מידי *amar lei v'i lav d'chata Reuven lo mahani lei l'Yosef
v'lo mi'idi*.
So he says I don't get it. According to you, he had
to have given something back to יוסף *Yosef* anyway, he had to
return the favor. So you're telling me that if ראובן *Reuven* hadn't
sinned, he wouldn't have given anything to יוסף *Yosef*? So, all right.
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* goes with that. אמר
ליה רבי יונתן רבך לאו הכי אמר *amar lei Rabbi Yonatan ravcha
lav hachi amar*.
That's not the way רבי יונתן *Rabbi Yonatan* your teacher said. But
here's what he said: ראויה היתה בכורה לצאת מרחל *re'uya hayta bechora
latzet me'Rachel*.
Meaning he says you can't just attribute it and it seems to
be like responding a little bit to what I'm saying. That's making
it all too somehow too personal or not fitting in with enough
sense of like destiny. According to you, he was going to give
something to יוסף *Yosef* anyway, it didn't require the specific circumstances of
the fact that ראובן *Reuven* lost the בכורה *bechora*. He had to
anyway return the favor, whatever. We need to make it something that's
a little more, I would say,
fateful in the sense that יוסף *Yosef* is going to get it.
So here's the way to explain it. That really יוסף *Yosef* all
along, the firstborn... Of the tribes of יעקב, Yaakov's יעקב's Yaakov, first
son should have been the first son with the wife that he
wanted to marry, with רחל. Rachel. So יוסף was his virtual first
son, right? And you know, I mean look, a lot of the
whole stories of בראשית, Bereishit, I assume people know this, you know,
if you want a fancy word, it's the usurpation of the right
of primogeniture. I love saying that 'cause it's two words, two fancy
words. Anyway, it's the uprooting of the right of the firstborn, right?
It starts all the way going back to, you know, קין Kayin
and הבל, Hevel, right? And אברהם Avraham doesn't seem to be a
first son, יצחק Yitzchak is not a first son, יעקב Yaakov is
not a first son, יוסף is not a first son. And the
irony is, of course, in דברים Devarim where it all says like
he has two wives, one is beloved and one is hated, he
cannot give the firstborn, לא יוכל לבכר את בן האהובה על פני
בן השנואה הבכור, lo yuchal levaker et ben ha'ahuva al penei ben
hasnu'ah habechor, which is of course exactly what יעקב Yaakov, did. He
had two wives, right, that לאה Leah was שנואה, snu'ah,
and he gave the בכור bechor, to יוסף who was the firstborn
of the wife who is the beloved wife. You know, so it's
very interesting, right, the way that the law sort of keeps the
way society has to be structured, you have to follow the norms
of society, you know, keep the maintain the structure of society. But
the whole narrative of the תורה Torah is that it goes to
who is deserving, not to who society sort of has identified by
right. And even when they go down to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
you know, what I mean, whatever, what does God
say to משה? Moshe? בני בכורי ישראל. beni bechori Yisrael. Well, we're
not actually the first nation on the earth, we're not God's firstborn,
but we are the בכור bechor. in the sense of the worthy,
right, chosen as the בכור bechor because of your worth. So there's
this whole dual narrative sort of like going on, and that's what
the גמרא Gemara here is picking up. It is saying like the
deserved firstborn goes to יוסף. Except what the גמרא Gemara is doing
here though, right, is sort of saying not just deserved because he
was more meritorious, but almost like should have actually literally been the
firstborn because this was the wife that יעקב Yaakov's would have wanted
to have married first and therefore should have been in a same
way that's very similar of course to the what do you call
it, to the יוסף and יצחק Yitzchak and ישמעאל Yishmael story. יצחק
Yitzchak was the firstborn of his true wife, of his like beloved
wife. It doesn't, it's not true with the יעקב Yaakov and עשו
Eisav story. Yes, Rabbi Joe.
I see all these layers, all these layers of irony and conflict
are there. It seems to be, don't you think, that the rights
and privileges of a firstborn don't go simply by status but by
merit, but it always ends up that it's the absolute youngest that
is meritorious so to speak.
Well, יוסף isn't the youngest.
Well, does that the only foil here is בנימין? Binyamin? But it's
not so right.
That's true too.
If everything you said is absolutely true I think, plus, right,
but the only time you have more than one to choose from
is בני יעקב, Bnei Yaakov, so I'm not sure whether you can
make the emphasize the youngest in the sense that
somehow יוסף has to be experienced as the
youngest vis-a-vis
ראובן, I can't explain
בנימין.
Binyamin. Otherwise I don't know what בנימין Binyamin is.
Right, right, right.
Yeah. It's also interesting, it's not like if he married רחל Rachel
first, she would have had יוסף first.
Right, like her years and years.
Well, that's true too. That's a good point.
Like they were, he was married to both of them.
That's a good point too. You're right, you're right. That's an excellent
point. Okay, so now anyway, let's take a look. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this. So he says, look,
you can't say just it's just because he wanted to return a
favor. It's got to be as I'm saying more fateful than that.
The way the רשב"ם Rashbam says it also is if he just
wanted to return a favor, he would have returned it from some
like his own property, not from taking away from one of the
brothers. So that's what the רשב"ם Rashbam reads in like, you don't
return a favor at somebody else's expense, so why are you taking
away from a brother to give to יוסף? Anyway, so we want
to make it more fateful. So he says, אלא רבי יוחנן רבך
לא כך אמר. ella Rabbi Yochanan ravcha lo kach amar. That's not
how רבי יוחנן, your rabbi, your teacher, said. Here's how he explained,
okay? He explained the following way: ראויה הייתה בכורה לצאת מרחל. re'uya
hayta bechora latzet mi-Rachel. דכתיב אלה תולדות יעקב
יוסף. de-ketiv elleh toldot Yaakov Yosef. Here are the generations of יעקב,
Yaakov, יוסף. So like, you know, that's always the funny word תולדות.
toldot. Does תולדות toldot mean like the descendants or does it mean
like the stories of? But if you read it as descendants, אלה
תולדות יעקב יוסף, elleh toldot Yaakov Yosef, so יוסף is being put
as the firstborn of יעקב. Yaakov אלא שקדמתה לאה ברחמים. ella she-kidmatah
Leah be-rachamim.
לאה Leah prayed and was able to be the first wife and
have the first son. ומתוך צניעות שהייתה בה ברחל, u-mitoch tzni'ut she-hayta
bah be-Rachel,
but because רחל Rachel was so modest and צנועה, tzenu'ah, החזירה הקדוש
ברוך הוא לה. hechzirah Hakadosh Baruch Hu lah. So God ultimately gave
the, you know, לאה's Leah firstborn son ראובן was the בכור bechor?
by birth and the title of בכור, bechor, but the rights of
the firstborn were restored to יוסף. יוסף'ס Yosef's to רחל'ס Rachel's firstborn
to יוסף. So he got the rights and ראובן got the name
because she was, she should have been it and because of her
modesty. So now we're going to see what that means for modesty.
So מאי דמטא לאברכנים, Mai d'matai l'avrachanim, so now everybody knows this
because it's in רש"י Rashi and it's in every single מדרש Midrash
says and you know so many people probably already think it's in
the פסוקים. Anyway, so what does it mean that לאה Leah preceded
רחל Rachel by prayers? דכתיב D'ksiv
רחמים rachamim often means that acts of prayer, like you know רחמי
rachmei who is the referred word that the גמרא Gemara has for
תפילה because it's an asking of compassion from God. Okay, דכתיב ועיני
לאה רכות. D'ksiv ve-einei Leah rakot. לאה'ס Leah's eyes were soft, were
so מאי רכות? mai rakot? What does it mean that they were
soft? אילימא Ilei-ma רכות, rakot, normally nowadays we say soft eyes is
probably like a compliment, right? Like means whatever, but anyway, but it
somehow clearly was not meant there as a compliment. מאי אילימא רכות
ממש? Mai ilei-ma rakot mamash? אפשר שבגנות בהמה טמאה לא דיבר הכתוב?
Efshar she-begnus behema tme'ah lo dibber hakasuv?
The תורה Torah! doesn't even want to say negative things about a
non-kosher
animal, דכתיב מן הבהמה הטהורה ומן הבהמה אשר איננה טהורה. d'ksiv min
ha-behema ha-tehora u-min ha-behema asher einena tehora. From the from the pure
animal, from the animal that's not pure, doesn't even want to use
the word טמאה tme'ah which is, you know, has negative valence, it
rather says not טהורה tehora right rather than saying טמאה. tme'ah. So
if that's true about animals, בגנות צדיקים דיבר הכתוב? b'gnus tzaddikim dibber
hakasuv?
It's going to say something negative about the righteous people, about לאה?
Leah? So even though, you know, it's just a physical characteristic, but
it doesn't matter, it's saying it, it's clearly it's clearly, you know,
not a complimentary thing to be saying. אלא אמר רבי אלעזר שמתנותיה
ארוכות. Ella amar Rabi Elazar she-matnoteha aruchos. So it's not רכות, rakot,
it's ארוכות. aruchos. That and I don't know how how we word
the word in מתנותיה, matnoteha, the gifts that she received were long.
She's her children will receive large gifts. What does that mean? Because
her children
are לוי Levi that gets the מתנות כהונה, matnot kehuna, the gifts
of the כהונה, kehuna, and her child is יהודה Yehuda who's going
to get the kingship. So she's going to be, you know, bestowed
with many gifts. Where do you get that from עיני? einei? I
have no idea, like עין ayin maybe is like a sense of
a wellspring and a ברכה, bracha, I really don't know. What?
Okay, anyway, yes, I actually think it might be the פשט pshat
in the פסוק pasuk might be positive. I think it is. In
other words, she had beautiful
עיני רכות einei rakot ורחל היתה יפת תואר ויפת מראה. v'Rachel hayta
yefat to'ar v'yefat mareh.
רחל Rachel and לאה Leah both by cows, or I got or
right as לאה Leah I think well רחל Rachel
is
a sheep, the way the גמרא Gemara is treating it.
Exactly, but I think also לאה Leah is a parallel to רחל,
Rachel, I think it's a type of
like in some Semitic languages I think it's an animal and she's
got soft, like soft large eyes, like a cow, cow-like eyes. The
פשט pshat might be
רכות rakot might be a compliment.
Yeah, but חכמים Chachamim always take it as negative, she her eyes
were dim, she couldn't see, she was... It's interesting. In לאה'ס Leah's
eyes were were not nice, but רחל'ס Rachel's were all-around nice. I
hear.
All right, somebody can go ahead and check in your see if
you have an עין רכות ayin rakot elsewhere in תנ"ך Tanakh and
tell me what it means. Was there? Okay. All right, we're fine.
I hear that as a possible read, okay? You can now go
all do your homework and check if the word עיניים רכות einayim
rakot appears anywhere else in תנ"ך Tanakh or in parallel Semitic language,
that cognates, I wanted to say cognates. Okay, anyway, so רבא אמר
לעולם רכות
ממש. Rava amar l'olam rakot mamash.
Okay,
no, no, no, it does mean soft. ולא גנאי הוא לה אלא
שבח הוא לה, v'lo gnai hu lah ella shevach hu lah, שבח
הוא לה. shevach hu lah. Not because of you, not because it's
physically attractive, we're not reading it as physical attraction, אלא שהיתה שומעת
פרשת דרכים, ella shehayta shoma'at parashat drachim, בני אדם bnei adam שהיו
אומרים, shehayu omrim, שני בנים יש לה לרבקה, shene banim yesh lah
l'Rivka, שתי בנות יש לו ללבן. shte banot yesh lo l'Lavan.
So there רבקה Rivka has two sons, לבן Lavan her brother has
two daughters. גדולה לגדול וקטנה לקטן. Gedola l'gadol u-ketana l'katan.
So the we'll assume the older cousin will marry the older cousin
and the younger cousin marry the younger cousin.
והיתה יושבת על פרשת דרכים, v'hayta yoshevet al parashat drachim, so she
was there on the crossroads, ומשאלת, u-mash'elet, גדול מה מעשיו? gadol ma
ma'asav? Oh,
so if I'm intended for the older son, tell me what is
he like? Notice he also says not how does he look? What
is he like? What are his actions like? What's his character like?
איש רע הוא, ish ra hu, oh, he's an evil person. מלסטם
בריות, melastem briyot, he you know he he's a bandit, he goes
ahead and he like he attacks people. קטן מה מעשיו? katan ma
ma'asav? How about the younger one? Oh, him? איש תם יושב אוהלים,
ish tam yoshev ohalim, oh,
he's a wonderful young man. Okay, he sits in tents.
Okay, this is for יעקב.
Yaakov
Right,
right, it's completely based on the inverse of יעקב. Yaakov Well, you
could also say עשו Eisav. was איש ציד איש שדה, Ish Tzayid
Ish Sadeh, which is making ציד Tzayid broaden it. But right, it's
all how חזל Chazal read עשו. Eisav It's not explicit. Okay, yes,
חזל Chazal read all the stories of עשו Eisav. through that lens.
ובכתה, U-vachata, she would cry עד שנשרו ריסיה ad she-nashru riseiha until
her eyelashes fell out from all the crying. Eyelashes, thank you, eyelashes.
That's beautiful, just the beginning, fine.
Fine, I understand, we're staying within the מדרש. Midrash. We've heard the
different read. והיינו דכתיב, Ve-hainu de-chtiv,
so therefore yes her eyes were, her eyelashes had fallen out, they
didn't look nice, fine. But the not looking nice was a positive
statement about her. It's not all about physical appearance. The not looking
nice shows how much she cared about marrying a צדיק, Tzaddik, a
righteous man. והיינו דכתיב Ve-hainu de-chtiv וירא ה׳ כי שנואה לאה Vayar
Hashem ki senuah Leah
and God saw that Leah was
hated. מאי שנואה? Mai senuah? What does it mean hated? אילימא
שנואה ממש, Ilima senuah mamash, literally יעקב
hated
her? אפשר בגנות בהמה טמאה לא דיבר הכתוב בגנות צדיקים דיבר הכתוב?
Efshar bi-gnut behemah temeah lo diber ha-katuv, bi-gnut tzaddikim diber ha-katuv? So
now it's about יעקב. Is it possible the תורה Torah would not
say bad things about animals, it'd say bad things about righteous people?
So who's the bad thing, it's interesting. You could say it's bad
about יעקב, it's bad about יעקב's character that he hated his wife.
But it could also be, you don't want to go ahead and
announce,
it's like, we tend to do blaming of the victim, right? If
somebody is hated, we don't always assume that that means that the
person who's doing the hating is doing the wrong thing. It makes
us look poorly on the person who's hated as well. So could
be here we're once again referring to לאה. Leah. Like you wouldn't
describe לאה Leah as שנואה senuah if that would actually then lead
to a derogatory association with לאה. Leah. אלא ראה הקדוש ברוך הוא
ששנואין מעשה עשו בפניה. Ela ra'ah Hakadosh Baruch Hu she-snu'in ma'aseh Eisav
be-faneha. It doesn't mean she was hated, it means that she hated
the evil actions of עשו. Eisav, ויפתח את רחמה Vayiftach et rachmah
and God opened up her womb. Okay, so that was why לאה
Leah merited to have the בכור. bechor, She merited to have the
בכור Bechor because she was so righteous, she wanted to marry יעקב,
she wanted only a righteous husband, and because of that, that was
her, her eyes, but that was in general why God made it
that she would have the firstborn son. Okay, right. ומאי צניעות היתה
ברחל? U-mai tzniyut haytah be-Rachel? And so what was רחל's Rachel's modesty
that allowed her son to re-merit the בכורה, or re-merit the rights
of the
בכור? Bechor דכתיב ויגד יעקב לרחל כי אחי אביה הוא. De-chtiv Vayaged
Yaakov le-Rachel ki achi aviha hu. יעקב says to רחל Rachel that
he was her father's brother. וכי בן רבקה הוא? Ve-chi ben Rivkah
hu? And רבקה's Rivkah's son. So he wasn't her father's brother, he
was her father, well as the גמרא's Gemara gonna say, והלא בן
אחות אביה הוא? Va-halo ben achot aviha hu? He's her father's sister's
son, not her father's brother. Of course what it's doing is it's
sort of saying since I'm רבקה's Rivkah's son it's like I'm in
רבקה's Rivkah's stead and therefore it's like I'm your father's brother. Okay
but anyway but he's the cousin. אלא אמר לה מינסבת לי? Ela
amar lah minsabat li? So here's what happened. He said to רחל,
Rachel, marry me. אמרה ליה אין. Amrah leh in. She said yes.
מיהו אבא רמאה הוא, Mihu abba rama'ah hu, but I have to
warn you, my father is a deceiver. My father's a scoundrel. ולא
יכלת ליה, Ve-lo yachlat leh, you will not manage
to stand up or to handle him. He's gonna get the better
of you if you want to marry me, you gotta be on
your lookout. אמר לה, Amar lah, so he said to her, מאי
רמאותיה? Mai ramauteih? How, what is his manner of deception? אמרה ליה,
Amrah leh, or like how, in what way will he try to
deceive you? אמרה ליה, Amrah leh, she said to him, אית לי
אחתא דקשישא מינאי, it li achata de-kashisha minai, I have a sister
that's older than me, ולא מנסבא לי קמה, ve-lo minsaba li kammah,
and he won't allow me to get married before her.
אמר לה, Amar lah, so that could just be a legitimate objection,
my father's gonna say no. But he's not saying my father's gonna
say no, my father's going to deceive you. He's going to say
yes but it's really going to be a no. Okay. אמר לה,
Amar lah, he said to her, אחיו אני ברמאות, achiv ani be-rama'ut,
so אחי אביה הוא. achi aviha hu. I am his equal, I
know how to be a deceiver just as well as he does.
Of course which is the whole ongoing story there with יעקב, about
the whole sheep and the whole thing and so on. Right, we're
not going to get into now the whole discussion about יעקב's character
and how that plays out. אמר לה, Amar lah, I mean but
it also goes back to his dealings with עשו, Esav, how he
represented himself, and of course that's part of the whole story. He
represented himself as the older son in order to get the בכור,
Bechor, so he got the younger
one... the older woman was represented as the younger in order to...
and he was sort of equally deceived. And that I assume people
know that's of course the pointed nature of the פסוק of לא
יעשה כן במקומנו לתת הצעירה לפני הבכירה. lo ye'aseh chen bi-mkomenu latet
hatze'irah lifnei habechirah. Like I don't know back where you come from,
I know you tend to mix up who goes first and who
doesn't, you put yourself before your brother, but here we keep the
firstborn first. All right, so that's obviously all of
it. Oh, you mean because his mother sort of encouraged him.
I'll take your curse. Right, and he listened to her.
Yeah. Well, I tell you to see you. What? What I tell
you in the lentil thing. Yeah.
Well, that's true, right. That was taking advantage, that wasn't deceiving.
Right, but it was his own initiative to try
to get the בכור, Bechor right. All right, moving on. All right.
Anyway, אחי אני ברמאות. Achi ani b'rama'ut. Okay, I'm his equal. Okay,
so ואמרה ליה, V'amrah leh,
she said to him, ומי שרי לצדיקי לסגויי ברמאותא? U'mi sharei l'tzaddiki
l'saguyei b'rama'uta?
Is it permitted for righteous people to walk in a way of
deception? הין. Hin. Yes.
עם נבר תתבר
ועם עקש תתפל.
Im
navar titbar v'im ikesh titapal.
If you are with a, I don't know how they translate נבר
navar
there. Scoundrel? Act in a scoundrel way. And if with a deceptive
person, you shall also act deceptively. So, yes, if that's the people
you're dealing with, that's how you have to act. You know, it
became a very interesting issue in general, right, when you're dealing with
a powerful force, you know, you're the disempowered minority, whatever. This was
the story of the Jews in גלות. Galus. You know, יעקב is
the example of the גלות Galus Jew, right? Sometimes, you know, you're
not in a position to act on equal terms and you, so,
you know, that became, right, how did the non-Jews feel for thousands
of years? I don't know how they translate.
Oh, they say it's the pure.
עם נבר תתבר.
Im
navar titbar.
Oh, it's the pure. Oh, that, the pure act pure. Ah, that's
better. That's better. Like בר לבב. Bar levav. Oh, that's okay, thank
you. That's a better... thank you, thank you. I didn't, I don't
know, I didn't look at the translation beforehand. Okay, you're right. Thank
you. If with the pure, act in a pure way, and with
the perverted, you should act in a deceptive way. Okay, thank you
Michael. Yeah, that's obviously a much better read of the... right, you
know, a better read. Okay. Anyway, but like I said, this was
always, you know, the challenge of the Jews in exile, right? How
much... you know, it's actually interesting, we mentioned the other time also
because this came up with, you know, with בנות צלפחד Benos Tzelofchad
and with רות. Rus. We're about to read... we're beginning with בנות
צלפחד, Benos Tzelofchad, we're about to read רות. Rus. You know, it's
a lot of the narratives of women in תנ"ך Tanakh is also,
how do you, if you're not, you know, if you're the disempowered
class, you know, how do you sort of manage to try to
get your way in society? Right? So the way that sort of
like רות Rus and בנות צלפחד, Benos Tzelofchad, both of them are
sort of stories about sort of some degree of manipulation because, you
know, you're not in a position of power. But is it a
deceptive manipulation or a non-deceptive manipulation, right? So the whole story about
בנות צלפחד, Benos Tzelofchad, we said this before, right? They come and
say, "Oh, look, you know, למה יגרע שם אבינו מתוך משפחתו? Lama
yigara shem avinu mitoch mishpachto? Why will our father's name be lost?"
They weren't saying we deserve on our own account. No, no, no,
no. We're doing it for the sake of our father. So you
have to somehow play within the assumptions and the structures of the
powers that be, right, and how do you sort of manage that
reality? So here, sometimes it comes through, how... comes through real deception.
Yes.
The daughters of לוט Lot did that and said that also about
their father.
Nice. That's the point.
The mechanical alignment's through there and through...
oh, that's a nice, that's a very interesting point. I hadn't made
that connection. You're right, about the daughters of לוט, Lot, very good.
And then that gets, gets you back to רות. Rus. Excellent. Okay,
got some good שמועס תורה shmuess Torah over here. Okay, ועם... okay,
so עם נבר תתבר, with the pure act purely, thank you. ועם
עקש תתפל, V'im ikesh titapal, and with those that are the perverted,
you shall act deceptively. So מסר לה סימנין. Masar lah simanim. So
here's how we're going to, to subvert your father's deception. Here are
some secret signs, okay, a secret handshake or whatever it is, and
therefore if he tries to pass off your sister as you, we'll
know that it's you because... I mean I'll know that it's not
you because you won't know the secret signs. Okay. כי קא מייתי
לה ללאה, Ki ka mayiti lah l'Leah,
so when then he produced לאה Leah
into the tent,
לבן... Lavan... excuse me, you got me all confused, right, לבן Lavan
brought לאה Leah into the tent. סברה השתא מיכספא אחתאי. Savrah hashta
michsafah achtai. Now my sister will be embarrassed because, you know, it's
going to become public that now she was... and she's going to
be like rejected in front of everybody. So one wonders why she
did not think about this ahead of time. Okay, but anyway, it
happened that way.
Yeah, that's true, until it becomes real people and the real event,
right, you really coming right to terms with it. מסרתינהו ניהלה, Masartinhu
nihalah, so she gave the secret signs to her sister. והיינו דכתיב
ויהי בבקר והנה היא לאה. V'hainu d'chtiv vayihi vaboker v'hineh hi Leah.
And it was in the morning and look, it was לאה. Leah.
מכלל דעד השתא לאו לאה היא? Michlal d'ad hashta lav Leah hi?
It sounds like until that time he didn't realize it was לאה,
Leah, which is certainly what the פשוטו peshuto sounds like, right? He
only discovered it in the morning. How could that be? He only
discovered it in the morning? אלא מתוך סימנין שמסר ליעקב לרחל ומסרתן
ללאה, Ela mitoch simanin shemasar l'Yaakov l'Rachel u'masartan l'Leah, because of the
secret signs that he gave to רחל, Rachel, רחל Rachel gave to
לאה, Leah, לא הוה ידע לה, Lo hava yada lah, he didn't
know עד ההיא שעתא, Ad hahi sha'ata, until that moment. Okay.
And she's saying to him that her father was going to deceive
him.
Ah, she's the one that deceives him. And all this time, he
thinks she's being righteous. And she's being righteous in her deception.
And he loves her more.
Okay, excellent. All right guys, excellent, excellent. Okay, okay, anyway, now, okay,
so now we got why that was a long of classic מדרש
Midrash and I'm sure you all have heard, but it's about how
why both ראובן is the בכור Bechor and יוסף is the בכור
bechor because, you know, one way you could say it is ראובן
was the actual בכור, bechor יוסף was the בכור bechor of the,
you know, got the rights of the בכור bechor because of the
beloved wife. But here it doesn't just make it the beloved wife,
it makes it in a sense almost like she had been destined
originally to have the firstborn, the youngest wife to the youngest son,
right? But because of, but לאה Leah sort of intervened, her prayers,
and then רחל Rachel re-merited it, etc. Okay, so now because we're
dealing with like יעקב'ס Yaakov's children, we're going to have a little
bit of another of a digression. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this: בכללן b'chlalan when if you look at the total number
of those that go down to מצרים, Mitzrayim. it says right: כל
הנפש הבאה ליעקב, kol hanefesh haba l'Yaakov, or did I skip a
line?
אלא מתוך סימנים, ela mitoch simanim, לא הוה ידע עד ההיא שעתא.
lo hava yada ad hahee shaata. בעי מיניה אבא חליפא קרויא מרבי
חייא בר אבא. ba'ei minei Aba Chalifa Karuya mi'Rebbe Chiya bar Abba.
So אבא חליפא Aba Chalifa asked רבי חייא בר אבא: Rebbe Chiya
bar Abba: בכללן אתה מוצא שבעים. b'chlalan ata motze shivim.
When you see the sum of how many people went down to
יעקב, it says: כל הנפש לבית יעקב הבאים מצרימה
שבעים. kol hanefesh l'veit Yaakov haba'im Mitzrayma shivim. Okay. בפרטן, b'fretam, but
if you actually count the names, okay, אתה מוצא שבעים חסר אחד,
ata motze shivim chaser echad, you only find 69.
And the רשב"ם Rashbam here points out that actually you see it's
already off when it counts the children of לאה, Leah, because when
it gives you the number of לאה, Leah, it says that they
are 33, I think, and there are only 32. One minute, where
does he say? מבני לאה, mi'bnei Leah, right. Oh, it says 33,
and they are actually only 32. So we know that we have
to make up the missing one with לאה'ס Leah's children. And by
the way, I should say that that sharpens the problem. Because if
it had just said 70 and it was 69, you could say
it's rounding, like the תורה says 40 and it means, you know,
39, or it says 50 and it means 49, like the counting
of the ספירה, Sefirah, like sometimes you could say it was rounding.
But it's not when it counts לאה Leah and it says 33
children and they're only 32, it's not rounding. So where is that
extra child that is, you know, of בני לאה? b'nei Leah?
Some people say that יעקב is included.
Maybe. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר ליה תאומה היתה
עם דינה. amar lei te'oma hayta im Dina. דינה Dina had a
twin. דכתיב ואת דינה בתו. dichtiv v'et Dina bito. And דינה. Dina.
The extra ואת v'et means she had a twin. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says: אלא מעתה תאומה היתה עם בנימין? ela me'ata te'oma
hayta im Binyamin? If that's true, let's say that בנימין Binyamin had
a twin. דכתיב ואת בנימין אחיו. dichtiv v'et Binyamin achiv. So every
if you say ואת v'et means a twin, so בנימין Binyamin had
a twin. So the גמרא Gemara says: then he mo', so he
said back: מרגלית טובה היתה בידי, margalit tova hayta b'yadi, you know,
I had this beautiful pearl, this beautiful
precious stone, precious idea, ואתה מבקש לאבדה ממני, v'ata mevakesh l'avdah mimeni,
and you're trying to make me lose it. Now what does that
mean? So the way so now he says: I have this great
explanation and now you're forcing me to tell it to you. So
how does it mean you're making me lose my beautiful pearl? So
the רשב"ם Rashbam. says: Well, now it's not just mine anymore. Now
it's going to be shared and publicized and everybody's going to know
it, and it's not going to be just my personal חידוש, chiddush,
which is I think a fascinating idea, which like now in the
age of like the internet, right, and the whole question of like
authorship and when you make your stuff, like so many things that
used to be private, you know, private ownership, authorship, right, are now
like public property, right? And it you sort of lose your ownership
over it or does it, you know, or does sort of the
way we think about ownership shift?
But you're supposed to share תורה!
I know! But this is what he said. Look at the רשב"ם.
Rashbam Okay, he says: מרגלית טובה תנא יקר בעיני כמרגלית שלא הייתי
רוצה לגלותה. margalit tova tana yakar b'einai k'margalit shelo hayiti rotze l'galota.
I wanted to keep it as mine.
ומעיקרא לכו... u'me'ikara l'cho... okay, והכא דחידודא הוא דקא בעי. v'hacha d'chidu
l'chi hayu dei ba'ei. The reason I said the ואת, v'et, I
was trying to sort of, you know, just like sharpen you, that
wasn't my real answer, but now you're forcing me to tell you
my real answer. לאבדה ממני כלומר לגלותה לאחרים, l'avdah mimeni klomar l'galota
l'acherim, ולחבב
הטעם הוא דאמר כן. u'lechaviev hatam hayu amar ken. So the רשב"ם
says, hey, he wasn't being serious. He was just trying to say
how beautiful it was. He wasn't really upset that he had to
share it. Okay, but anyway, I think it's an interesting idea. Like,
do you lose your תורה when you share it and it's no
longer your personal property, or does it increase, right? Anyway,
okay, so what's the reason? הכי אמר רבי חמא בר חנינא: hachi
amar Rebbe Chama bar Hanina: זו יוכבד שהורתה בדרך ולידתה בין החומות.
zo Yocheved she'harata baderech v'ladata bein hachomot. First of all, it's a
child of לאה, Leah, it's יוכבד, Yocheved, right, who was a descendant
who was a daughter of לוי, Levi, and that explains there was
only there was only 60 like לאה Leah had 32 children before
when it says when they were going down, it counts them and
it says that there were 32. But it says all of the
people who came were 70. So when they left they were 69,
right, and when they came they were 70. Okay, so that's how
it works. So: זו יוכבד שהורתה בדרך ולידתה בין החומות. zo Yocheved
she'harata baderech v'ladata bein hachomot. She was born once they entered into
the walls of מצרים. שנאמר אשר ילדה אותה ללוי במצרים. shenemar asher
yalda otah l'Levi b'Mitzrayim. So that she had been given birth to
her to לוי Levi in Egypt. לידתה במצרים, ladata b'Mitzrayim, her birth
was in Egypt, ואין הורתה במצרים, v'ein harata b'Mitzrayim, but she had
not been... conceived or been born in pregnancy in Egypt. So she
her
יוכבד'ס Yocheved's mother was pregnant with her the whole trip and when
they finally arrived they were 70. So those that left were 69
and those that arrived were 70. Okay. Alright. בעי מיניה רבי חלבו
מרבי שמואל בר נחמני: Ba'ei minei Rabbi Chelbo mei-Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani:
כתיב ויהי כאשר ילדה רחל את יוסף. Ksiv vayehi ka'asher yalda Rachel
es Yosef. It was when רחל Rachel gave birth to יוסף that
יעקב said to לבן, Lavan, he says, "give me my wife and
my children and I have to go back to my father." So
why was that all hinging on יוסף being born? מאי שנא כי
אתיליד יוסף? Mai shna ki isyelid Yosef? אמר ליה: why did he
all of a sudden say this just when יוסף was born? Why
was he waiting for that moment? So the גמרא Gemara says, ראה
יעקב אבינו שאין זרעו של עשו נמסר אלא ביד זרעו של יוסף,
Ra'ah Yaakov Avinu she-ein zaro shel Esav nimsar ela b'yad zaro shel
Yosef, because he saw that עשו'ס Esav's descendants, because he was going
to go back, what was going to happen as soon as he
was going to return? He encountered עשו, Esav right? And with 400
men, right? So he knew as soon as he turned to כנען
Kna'an he was going to have to face up to this brother
that he had wronged and that was with murderous intent. So he
needed to be prepared and he knew that the way he and
his future generations would be able to stand up against עשו Esav
was through the descendants of יוסף. So he himself realized that the
only way he'd be ready to face עשו Esav was once יוסף
was born. אלא ביד זרעו של יוסף, Ela b'yad zaro shel Yosef,
שנאמר והיה בית יעקב אש ובית יוסף להבה ובית עשו לקש. shene'emar
vehaya veis Yaakov eish uveis Yosef lehava uveis Esav l'kash. The house
of יעקב will be a fire and the house of יוסף a
flame and the house of עשו Esav. will be for stubble and
for straw. So therefore he knew that he needed יוסף to be
born before he was ready to encounter עשו. Esav איתיביה. Eisivye. Now
I'll ask you on that. Really? You're telling me that we've never
been victorious over עשו Esav. without the assistance of the descendants of
יוסף? But it says by דוד: David: ויכם דוד מהנשף ועד הערב.
Vayakem David mei-haneshef ve'ad ha'erev. דוד David smote them from the dawn
until the evening. This is talking about עמלק. Amalek. למחרתם Lamochorasam of
the next day. אמר ליה: so and דוד David was a descendant
of יהודה, Yehuda, מיהודה, mi-Yehuda, not of יוסף. So אמר ליה: he
said back to him, דאקרייך נביאי לא אקרייך כתובי. D'akrayach Nevi'ei lo
akrayach Ksuvei. For the one who taught you נביאים Nevi'im never taught
you כתובים. Kesuvim. Very good. You were able to quote a פסוק
in שמואל. But did you learn דברי הימים? Divrei Hayamim. כתיב, because
it says there: ובלכתו ציקלג נפלו
עליו
ממנשה. Uvlecho Tziklag naflu alav mi-Menashe. Okay, when he went, when דוד
David went to Tziklag to fight against
עמלק, Amalek, they descended upon עמלק Amalek also from the tribe of
מנשה, Menashe, who is descendant of יוסף. And who were part of
that battle? עדנה ויוזבד וידיעאל ומיכאל ויוזבד ואליהוא וצלתי ראשי האלפים אשר
למנשה. Adnah ve-Yozavad vi-Yediael u-Micha'el ve-Yozavad ve-Elihu ve-Zilsai rashei ha-alafim asher l'Menashe.
דוד David had assistants from the tribe of מנשה. Menashe. So you
needed to have read דברי הימים. Divrei Hayamim מתיב רב יוסף. Maseiv
Rav Yosef. Now רב יוסף Rav Yosef asks,
one minute: ומהם בני שמעון הלכו להר שעיר. Umeihem b'nei Shimon halchu
l'Har Se'ir. Here's another פסוק from דברי הימים that people from the
descendants of שמעון Shimon went to הר שעיר, Har Se'ir, שעיר Se'ir
we know is עשו. אנשים חמש מאות ופלטיה ונעריה ורפיה ועוזיאל בני
ישעי בראשם. Anashim chameish mei'os u-Platya ve-Na'arya u-Rfaya ve-Uziel b'nei Yish'i b'rosham.
Okay, so all of those people went. ויכו את שארית הפלטה לעמלק
Vayaku es she'eris ha-pleita l'Amalek and they destroyed the remnants of עמלק.
Amalek. וישבו שם עד היום הזה Vayeshvu sham ad hayom hazeh and
they're still dwelling there till this day. So that's all from שמעון,
Shimon, not from יוסף. So אמר רבה בר שילא: Amar Rabba bar
Shila: ישעי מבני מנשה אתי. Yish'i mibnei Menashe asi. No, no, no,
the ישעי Yish'i person, he was actually, although it sounds like he
was part of שמעון, Shimon, really he was also a descendant of
מנשה. Menashe. דכתיב ובני מנשה חפר וישעי. Dichsiv uvnei Menashe Cheifer ve-Yish'i.
Now there's no פסוק that says "ובני מנשה חפר Cheifer וישעי", ve-Yish'i,
but there is a פסוק that says like they say something similar
to that and it's actually not חפר but it's עפר Eifer וישעי,
so it's close enough. Let's see. The הגה hagah says if you
look at the ג' מסורת הש"ס, Gimmel Masores HaShas, it says ואלה
ראשי בית אבותם ועפר וישעי. v'eileh rashei beis avosam v'Eifer v'Yish'i. All
right, so close enough. But anyway there is a ישעי Yish'i that's
associated with בני מנשה, b'nei Menashe, so we're able to maintain our
assertion that they only fall in the hand of בני יוסף. b'nei
Yosef. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Back to, that was a nice little
אגדתא passage, back to הלכה. תנו רבנן הבכור נוטל פי שנים בזרוע
ובלחיים ובקיבה. Tanu Rabbanan: Ha-bechor notel pi shenayim bazroa u-valchayim u-vakeiva. So
let's say you are a בכור bechor of a כהן, Kohen, a
firstborn of a כהן, Kohen, and your father died. And now somebody
wants to give a gift. Now he slaughters an animal, so the
כהן Kohen gets pieces of the animal. It doesn't, you know, he
can give it to any כהן Kohen he wants. But it's the
arm, the cheeks, and the maw, like one of the stomachs. Okay?
So he says he, the בכור bechor gets double of those gifts.
ובמוקדשין. U-vmukdashin.
Oh, we're going to discuss it. Because it's not obvious how that
makes sense. Okay. And in קרבנות. Korbanos. ובשבח ששבחו נכסים לאחר מיתת
אביהן. U-veshevach she-shavchu nechasim l'achar misas avihen. And in שבח, shevach, and
in any improvement of the estate after their father died. כיצד? Keitzad?
Now what does that mean? הניח להן אביהן פרה מוחכרת ומושכרת ביד
אחרים. Hiniach lahen avihen para muchkeres u-muskeres b'yad acherim. He left them
over a cow that was מוחכרת muchkeres basically means that somebody else
is doing business with it and splitting the profits with the father,
and מושכרת muskeret just means a straight rental, או
שהייתה רועה בעפר, o she'haytah ro'ah b'afar, באפר, b'eifer, or it was
just grazing, וילדה v'yaldah and it gave birth, בכור נוטל פי שנים,
bechor notal pi shnayim, the בכור bechor gets double, אבל בנו בתים
ונטעו כרמים aval banu batim v'natu kramim but if you know, the
children built houses on the land, אין בכור נוטל פי שנים ein
bechor notal pi shnayim he doesn't get double. So that's going to
be very interesting. Like why does he get all this stuff that
sounds like ראוי, ra'uy, not מוחזק, muchzak, right? Stuff that comes after
the death that he shouldn't get double. And if he's getting double
by certain types of stuff that improves on its own, why doesn't
he get it by other stuff that improves on its own? So
we're going to see that. But the first thing we're going to
pay attention to is this זרוע לחיים וקיבה. zro'a lechayim v'keivah. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this, האי הזרוע והלחיים והקיבה היכי דמי,
hai hazro'a v'halechayim v'hakeivah heichi dami,
what's this case that he gets double of these gifts from the
animal? אי דאתו לידי אבוה i d'atu l'yadei avu'ah if the person
who slaughtered the animal gave these gifts to the father and then
the father died, פשיטא pishita of course he gets firstborn's, then it's
just part of the property of the father. ואי דלא אתו לידי
אבוה v'i d'lo atu l'yadei avu'ah if the father first died and
now this guy is coming along and looking to give these gifts
to a כהן, kohen, so ראוי הוא, ra'uy hu, so you know
even if the person like normally would usually give to the father,
it's stuff that the father is getting after he died, okay, ואין
הבכור נוטל בראוי כבמוחזק. v'ein habechor notal b'ra'uy k'v'muchzak. Something that was
fit to come to the father but the father wasn't already in
possession of, the בכור bechor doesn't get double, the בכור bechor, only
gets double in stuff the father was already in possession of. So
the גמרא says no, הכא במכירי כהונה עסקינן. hacha b'makirei kehunah askinan.
First of all we're dealing with a case of מכירי כהונה. makirei
kehunah. This was an institution that was around that was very often,
I mean unfortunately, you know it would be like the rich get
richer, the poor get poorer. It would cut out the whole idea
of right of כהנים kohanim is you imagine all the כהנים kohanim
come and they all get equal, but it would be that like
you know certain families of homeowners were always give to certain families
of כהנים kohanim which would tend to mean that some כהנים kohanim
would wind up being privileged and getting a lot of the gifts
and others would be out of the picture, okay? And that was
מכירי כהונה. makirei kehunah. So if this כהן kohen was one, was
like this was the כהן kohen I always give to. You could
imagine it on a personal level, oh he's my pal I always
give it to him. But it seems from other evidence that it
was a little bit more institutionalized, like families always gave to other
families. But anyway, if this is the one that I always give
to, then it's, it's to some degree because it's been so entrenched
and established that way, it's like he automatically has rights to it
even before I gave it to him. Okay, that's the חידוש chiddush
here. Okay, now one minute, as long as it was slaughtered, one
minute, דאישתחיט d'ishtachit and the animal had to be slaughtered. I mean
he only gets rights once it becomes the, the gift for the
כהן. kohen. בחיי דאבוהון b'chayei d'avuhon in the father's life, and not
only that, but you have to designate it, separate it out. Now
it's not like the animal was טבל, tevel, it doesn't work like
grain, it's not like you can't eat the animal, okay, but
nevertheless דקסבר מתנות שלא הורמו כמי שהורמו דמו. d'kasavar matnot shelo hurmu
k'mi shehurmu damu. The gifts of a כהן kohen even before they've
been separated, since you have to separate them off and give them
to a כהן, kohen, you look at it as if they've been
separated. So there's like a double חידוש chiddush here. You've just got
a dead animal, but you look at it as if already you've
separated out the portion of the כהן kohen and because you always
give it to a particular כהן, kohen, you look at it as
if that כהן kohen has already taken possession of it. Enough, maybe
not that he's an owner and this becomes an interesting concept, we
said you have to be מוחזק muchzak in it in order for,
in order to for the son to get a double portion. So
what תוספות Tosafot discusses is, is that there can be a concept
that even if you're not technically the owner yet, like let's say
this כהן kohen before he died there was מכירי כהונה, makirei kehunah,
you slaughtered this animal or whatever, he goes to a woman and
he says I'm מקדש mekadesh you with the, with you know with
that stuff in David's house. So it probably doesn't work, he probably
doesn't own it. But can you have a concept that he's sort
of like in possession of it without yet owning it because we
know it's going to him and it's, you know, and it has
to go to a כהן kohen and it's assigned to him? So
that's like an interesting question if we have that middle space. But
that's what it's saying. Because of that scenario, it's like he owned
it enough that when he dies it goes down and the, and
the בכור bechor gets double.
I think I'm confused about the relationship between the זרוע לחיים וקיבה
zro'a lechayim v'keivah and double portion. These three items, the זרוע לחיים
וקיבה zro'a lechayim v'keivah goes to a כהן kohen when I slaughter
an animal, I give up, I have to give, not קרבן.
korban. You slaughter an animal because you want the meat.
That's right, okay. So this is what I have to give to
a,
you find a כהן kohen and you give it to him. Right.
So you always give it to a particular כהן. kohen. You didn't
get around to giving it to him, he died. So now you're
going to give it to his family, but you're essentially giving it
to his family by virtue of the fact that you would have
given it to the father. Right. And the בכור bechor now takes
the double portion of it because it's like the father already received.
In other words out of his five כהן kohen brothers, right, I've
got the, I've got the זרוע לחיים וקיבה, zro'a lechayim v'keivah, the
בכור bechor takes double the amount of those three items from the
other four brothers.
Right. Exactly. Okay, so that's that. Let's just read the case of
the קדשים קלים. kodashim kalim. Okay, one more piece. Okay.
The קדשים קלים, kodashim kalim, so the גמרא says, I mean of
the of the מוקדשים, mukdashim, the גמרא says מוקדשים לאו דידיה נינהו.
mukdashim lav dideih ninhu. What do we mean that he gets double
of the portion? Like if a guy's bringing a חטאת, chatat, I
mean if it's my חטאת chatat and I'm bringing, and so if
this כהן's Kohen dead, he's not doing the עבודה avodah in the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. What, his sons now are getting double? Like
that doesn't make any sense. And if it's the father's חטאת, chatat,
so, you know, it's not his anyway, it belongs to the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. We're not considered an owner that you pass down
your קרבן korban to your children. So the גמרא says, no, בקדשים
קלים ואליבא דרבי יוסי הגלילי. be-kodashim kalim ve-aliba de-Rabbi Yosi HaGelili. We're
talking about a שלמים. shlamim. And a שלמים, shlamim, since basically the
owner eats all the meat of the שלמים, shlamim, right, you give
a little to the כהן, Kohen, the innerds go on the altar,
but basically the owner eats pretty much all the meat. So that's
considered still to be owned by, at least according to רבי יוסי
הגלילי, Rabbi Yosi HaGelili, even though it's going to be offered as
a קרבן, korban, you're still the owner of it. Okay. ואליבא דרבי
יוסי הגלילי דאמר ממון בעלים הוא, ve-aliba de-Rabbi Yosi HaGelili de-amar mammon
ba'alim hu, that a שלמים shlamim is considered to be the property
of the owner. And again, if he gave it to a woman,
he could marry her with it. It's giving her something of value
that he owns. And therefore, if a כהן Kohen is מקדיש makdish
a שלמים, shlamim, really if anybody is מקדיש makdish a שלמים shlamim
and then dies, the בכור, the kids are going to bring it
and now the בכור is going to be entitled to get a
double portion of the meat when they come to eat it.
Okay, as it's taught in a ברייתא, Baraisa, ומעלה מעל בה', u-ma'ala
ma'al b'Hashem, somebody denies somebody, you entrusted an object to me,
וכחש בעמיתו, ve-kichash ba-amito, I deny that you entrusted it to me
and I take an oath, and it says I trespass against God.
So the פשט pshat of the פסוק is I trespass against God
because I swore falsely to you. But רבי יוסי הגלילי's Rabbi Yosi
HaGelili reading it is that the object actually somewhat belongs to God
as well. I could be stealing from you by denying that I'm
holding onto your object, but it's an object that's also stealing from
God, that also belongs to God. What type of an object is
that? A שלמים. shlamim. Okay, you had me hold onto your שלמים
shlamim animal before you sacrificed it, and then I deny it, I'm
denying you your object, and I'm also denying something that is a
sanctified object. לרבות קדשים קלים שהן ממון בעלים דברי רבי יוסי הגלילי.
lerabbos kodashim kalim shehen mammon ba'alim divrei Rabbi Yosi HaGelili. Okay, that's
what רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosi HaGelili says. So therefore, now this
isn't limited to a כהן. Kohen. Anybody sanctifies an animal, it's a
שלמים shlamim and he dies, his children bring the קרבן, korban, and
the בכור gets double the meat according to רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi
Yosi HaGelili because that is actually considered to be the meat of
the owner, as opposed to other קרבנות, korbanos, whoever eats the meat,
the concept is משולחן גבוה קזכו, mishulchan gavoah kazchu,
they're eating God's meat, they're eating off of God's table. But by
a שלמים, shlamim, you know, it's, you know, you think of it
differently. Now technically speaking, actually, after the שלמים shlamim is brought as
a sacrifice, we also think of it as eating off of God's
table, but nevertheless, once it was, while it was still alive, it
was considered to be your property and the בכור was a double
owner, so therefore he's entitled to double the portion of the meat.
All right, we will pick up with this tomorrow.